<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Neophuto-astrologos. = The novice-astrologer instructed in a New-Years-gift to Mr. William Lilly; occasioned by the scurrility, scandal, ignorance, and flattery of his Merlin for the ensuing year. With two dedicatory epistles; the one to the learned divines, the other to the honest astrologers of this nation. / By G.J. or J.G. which Lilly the parasite pleaseth.</title>
            <author>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G93</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2112_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123655</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123655)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2112[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Neophuto-astrologos. = The novice-astrologer instructed in a New-Years-gift to Mr. William Lilly; occasioned by the scurrility, scandal, ignorance, and flattery of his Merlin for the ensuing year. With two dedicatory epistles; the one to the learned divines, the other to the honest astrologers of this nation. / By G.J. or J.G. which Lilly the parasite pleaseth.</title>
                  <author>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E.C. and are to be sold at the Royal Exchange, Westminster-hall, and Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.J. or J.G. = John Gadbury.</note>
                  <note>The first word of title is in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>The final two leaves = advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb. 23. 1659"; the 60 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilly, William, 1602-1681 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrologers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΝΕΟ'ΦΥΤΟ-'ΑΣΤΡΟ'ΛΟΓΟΣ: THE Novice-ASTROLOGER INSTRUCTED: IN A NEW-YEARS-GIFT TO Mr. <hi>William Lilly;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the Scurrility, Scandal, Ignorance, and Flattery of his Merlin for the enſuing year.</p>
            <p>With two Dedicatory Epiſtles; the One to the Learned Divines, the Other to the Honeſt Aſtrologers of this Nation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. J.</hi> or <hi>J. G.</hi> which <hi>Lilly</hi> the Paraſite pleaſeth.</p>
            <q>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool, then of him, <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Cretians are always lyars, evil beaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>Wherefore rebuke them ſharply <hi>[cuttingly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>]</hi> that they may be ſound in the faith, <bibl>
                  <hi>Tit. 1.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>E. C.</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Royal Exchange, Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:2"/>
            <head>To the Learned Divines of this Nation, whether Presbyterians, or Independents.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Learned Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough by reaſon of the ſelf-ends and private Intereſts of vain-glorious and ignorant perſons, the Science of Aſtrology hath had the misfortune to be thought repugnant to your Sacred Studies; yet if it be duly (and without prejudice) conſidered, they may not only both ſtand together, but be aſſiſting unto each other: <hi>The one, conſulting the Leſſer</hi> [though the more Divine] Book of Scriptures; the other, the Greater [and the more Natural] Book of Creatures.</p>
            <p>In ancient times, among the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> (as your learned ſelves well know) there were none admitted into your Holy Order without being veſted with a competent knowledge in Aſtrology. I readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the Errors vented, and Impoſturiſms practiſed under the Golden wings of this Art, are ſufficient to antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate your better thoughts from a ſerious Inſpection and examination thereof. And it were a thing ſuperlatively unjuſt, to enforce you, with the good Wine thereof, to drink the Dregs alſo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:3"/>
            <p>Aſtrology is a fair and beautifull Virgin, though by many rendred a Notorious ſtrumpet! The Fair <hi>Urania</hi> is every way moſt accompliſhed and lovely! It is my humble requeſt therefore, that you would not conſider it as it is rendred by Ignorant perſons practiſing it; but as it is (untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) in it ſelf. The Lute is a moſt melodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inſtrument, being touched by the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fingers of a Maſter in Muſick; but hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a Porter, or Carman, from a Barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door you may hear as pleaſing a ſound. It is Aſtrologies greateſt unhappineſs, that her <hi>pretended favorites</hi> are her <hi>greateſt enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learned Friends! The Deſign of this little Book is to take off the ugly and deformed vizzard from the face of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, that for many years it hath been compelled to wear, by the ſubtill cunning of one, who under pretence thereof hath been (<hi>ſine ratione, vel religione</hi>) too bold and ſawcy, not only with her, but your Learned ſelves. The Author hereof wiſheth all honour to a Learned ſetled Miniſtry, and Aſtrology freed from Sycophantique Practiſers; and that the learned Divine and honeſt Aſtrologer (as in times paſt) might ſhake hands with each other, and Divinity and Aſtrology ſtand together.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:3"/>
            <head>To the Honeſt Aſtrologers of this Nation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu need not wonder at the ſight, or ſubject of this ſmall Tractate; for it drives at nothing but</hi> the Salvage of Aſtrologers Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Credit, and your own Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>If you would know</hi> why I oppoſe Mr. Lilly, (<hi>who pretends himſelf the onely Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of</hi> Aſtrologie) <hi>it is becauſe</hi> he hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Art, and turned his back upon the truth thereof. <hi>Had he been true to the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, unto which he ſo largely pretends, I had forborn this pains, and prevented your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of peruſal:</hi> But he appearing ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant <hi>(as I have ſhewed)</hi> to his Art in every thing he writes, <hi>hath not onely made Shipwrack of his own Repute, but [like a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Prodigal] lays the Honour of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, and your ſelves (alſo) in the duſt.</hi> For what perſon is he, that can be brought to believe there is life and moiſture remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the ſmaller Trees, when the [pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended] Cedar is dry and ſapleſs?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:123655:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I well hoped that ſome of you (more able) would have eaſed me of this task,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask'd this Arch Pretender before now. <hi>But ſince his Errors are ſo eminently ſpread and promoted, to the great ſcandal of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, and hitherto no one hath offered to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion him</hi> — I adjudged it convenient <hi>(in recompence of his ſcurrilities)</hi> to ſtop his courſe at this time, leſt in the height of his folly, he ſurfeit more dangerouſly, and run mad beyond the cure of all probable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If, for this my pains, I am not requited with a</hi> Trepan, <hi>I ſhall not need to fear the force of my</hi> Antagoniſts Pen; <hi>being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to my ſelf, I have not miſ-repreſented him in a ſyllable. However, if he judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf injured, or find himſelf troubled at any thing in this Diſcourſe,</hi> let him, rationally, <hi>(not railingly)</hi> acquit himſelf from thoſe Errors charged upon him; or elſe by his ſilence, acknowledge himſelf as great an Impoſtor, as this Treatiſe pronounces him; <hi>that ſo the world may be undeceived, and the Honour of Your Selves and Art, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123655:4"/>
            <head>ΝΕΟ'ΦΥΤΟ-'ΑΣΤΡΟ'ΛΟΓΟΣ: The Novice-Aſtrologer INSTRUCTED: IN A NEW-YEARS-GIFT TO Mr. <hi>William Lilly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO ſooner came the <hi>Merlin</hi> of <hi>Lilly</hi> (that Arch-Paraſite) from the Preſs, flying about into the world, after its wonted rate; but being informed that he had brought his <hi>Legs to the Stocks,</hi> and his <hi>Stiff Neck to the Halter of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> I was deſirous to ſee whether he had acquitted himſelf <hi>like a true Penitent, ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſear'd Conſcience in the briniſh tears of Contrition;</hi> acknowledging (with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row) his Miſtakes committed, and all thoſe Errors and Ignorances charged upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123655:5"/>him, in the <hi>King of Swedes Nativity,</hi> and <hi>the Spurious Prognoſticator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But behold! upon a due Examination of this his pretended <hi>Recantation Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack,</hi> I finde him lyſping and jabbering after his wonted nonſenſical manner, as if he were every way uncapable of rendring one wiſe Sentence or Word in his own defence. And although he hath been ſo notably baited, even to the looſing <hi>the Noſe of his Reputation and Credit in the Art he profeſſeth,</hi> he paſſeth his <hi>Hunters</hi> like a ſlye Deer, and gives all their Checques, and Counter-Checques a fair go-by, even as he were none of their game, or any thing at all concerned in their chaſing him. Onely thus — (that you may adjudge him ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently heated and affrighted) he frisks up his dirty tayl in a fury, and like the <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Beaſt,</hi> ſquirts out his filth (thereby ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the better to eſcape) in the Faces of his Purſuers. — <hi>Complaining of his being hard dealt with by Stitching Pens, and by Botchers, not Artiſts; and that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him to anſwer a Boy, or impudent ranting Fool, that dares not own his name to be</hi> G. J. <hi>or</hi> J. G. ſays <hi>he ſhould render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ridiculous (being an Eagle, an Owl ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123655:5"/>to catch at a Flye;</hi> and inſinuates to his Readers, <hi>That he hath no Antagoniſts but Ranters and Atheists,</hi> (both which E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithets the beſt befit himſelf of any that I know.) After all which <hi>Billings-gate</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, (inſtead of a ſolid Vindication) with a company of Ignorant, Contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Groundleſs Quacks for the <hi>Swede,</hi> and a Bundle of Abuſes to Aſtrologers, and Aſtrologie beſide, — <hi>Exit Merlinus Anglicus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which Barbarous and Ridiculous Stuff, I need in ſtrictneſs, take no further notice then this — <hi>LILLY WRIT IT! A Fellow that cannot tell how to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but to raile onely! That knows nothing of Aſtrologie, but the name; which he makes uſe of, as a Cloak to cover his Ignorance! That knows neither how to take, or to make an Argument! That complies with any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſo that he may be thought the State-Aſtrologer!</hi> In which reſpects, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him beneath the revenge of the Pen of any ingenious Perſon or Scholar; and would have him therefore to know, that the grand reaſon why I ſet not my name at length in my Books againſt him, is, the probability of my purchaſing the cenſure
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123655:6"/>of the ingenious and learned Artiſts, for entering the Liſts <hi>per Nominem,</hi> with ſo baſe and low-orb'd a Fellow; unfitting for a Man to Cope with, much leſs an Artiſt.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, in regard of my promiſe to the world in my laſt Laſh of this Quack, entituled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; or, <hi>The Spurious Prognoſticator;</hi> and leſt that he ſhould cry Victory before he be harneſſed for the Battel, and ſo in his own conceit paſs for a Conqueror; — I will rip him up, and ſhew his Nakedneſs and Folly to the world, ſomewhat more largely then he hath done, although his own Pen hath been a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Index thereof, in his idle and addle Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for the enſuing year. Wherein (as briefly as I may) <hi>I will prove him to be the greatest Enemy to Aſtrologie that this age hath brought forth; a meer Ignorant in it, though he quack ſo much under the Canopy of it; an Illiterate, Abuſive, Pragmatical Fellow, void of Civility, Ingenuity and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may not looſe him in my Chaſe, I will obſerve the ſame Method as in my laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, to begin with <hi>his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;</hi> Secondly, his <hi>general Prog;</hi> Thirdly, his <hi>Monethly Fictions.</hi> And then I ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123655:6"/>appeal to the world, whether he be not an Owl, rather then an Eagle in Aſtrologie.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>His Epistle Examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIlliam Lilly</hi> in the beginning of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, makes his Introduction to his Excuſe, with a notorious Contradiction of himſelf, and a moſt high and injurious Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to Aſtrologie, and the ingenious Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents thereof, in theſe words—<hi>The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny turnings, and windings, and changes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in</hi> England <hi>in</hi> 1659. <hi>what Man or Angel could predict?</hi> — And a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle further he ſaith, — <hi>They</hi> (meaning the Changes, <hi>&amp;c.) were not in any way demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strable, or to be found out by the ſharpeſt Rules of Aſtrologie.</hi> Had Mr. <hi>L.</hi> been Friend, either to Himſelf, Aſtrologie, or Aſtrologers, he could never have made ſo Contradictious, Senſeleſs and Ridiculous an Excuſe: for (1.) herein, he gives the Lye to all that ever himſelf hath formerly, and now written: and (2.) he beſpatters all thoſe ingenious Artiſts that did predict
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123655:7"/>(and that from the known Rules of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie) thoſe many Changes that happened in <hi>England</hi> 1659. And (3) he caſts dirt in the beautiful Face of Aſtrologie it ſelf, inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an incertainty, or deficiency of its Rules and Aphoriſms, and a perfect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of any Man or Angel to predict thoſe Changes mentioned thereby.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He giveth the Lye most broadly and ſhamefully to himſelf;</hi> for in all his party<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works formerly, he rantingly (and ravingly alſo) argues againſt the Divines—<hi>That in the great Book of Heaven, are all Changes on Earth written; and that himſelf was born to predict them, ſometimes more tacitely, at other times more largely.</hi> See his Alm. 1655. and his Epiſtle to his Alm. 1658. in particular, where he ſays,—<hi>There is no Emergency, good or bad, that happens on Earth, but hath a full manifeſtation from the Configurations of the Heavens. And that</hi> Italy, France, <hi>and his</hi> Holineſs <hi>himſelf, have cauſe to remember how ominous his Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions have proved to them.</hi> Nay, he cracks more largely in his <hi>Worlds Cataſtrophe, — That what he cannot do by Common Rules of Aſtrologie, he can by Angels and Spirits:</hi> yea, ſo well is he acquainted with ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123655:7"/>Whimſies, and Vanities (as he proclaims it himſelf) <hi>that he ſhall go near</hi> (when time ſerves) <hi>to give every Nation of</hi> Europe <hi>a touch of its duration and continuance, from conſidering the Angel, or Genius of it.</hi> But now neither He, nor Man or Angel is able to predict any thing of Mundane Affairs, from the Rules of Aſtrologie: by which it conſpicuouſly appears, that Mr. <hi>L.</hi> and his skill alſo is ſubject to a ſtrange kind of Fluctuation.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Nunc huc, nunc illuc, exemplo nubis aquoſae.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Now here, ſoon there, much like a Watriſh Cloud.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>But tell me, Mr. <hi>L.</hi> canſt thou expect to paſs thus to the world undiſcovered, and ſtill be thought an Aſtrologer? Doſt thou think and believe, all men are as ignorant and contradictious as thy ſelf? If not,—
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh!</hi> William! William! <hi>monſtrous</hi> William Lilly!</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How cam'ſt thou here, to ſhew thy ſelf ſo ſilly?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>He abuſively beſpatters all ingenious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123655:8"/>Artiſts too.</hi> For, doth it handſomly follow, becauſe Mr. <hi>L.</hi> is ignorant in Aſtrology, and (by conſequence) of predicting thoſe eminent Changes which hapned in 1659. that therefore all Ingenious and true-born Artiſts are ſo too? If Mr <hi>L.</hi> like an unexpert traveller, miſſeth the way he is to go, and tumbleth into a Bog, or Quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, Muſt he therefore be angry at thoſe perſons acquainted with the Road, that they do not tumble in with him for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? What fault was it of Mr <hi>VVharton, Trigg, Tanner, Wing, Gadbury,</hi> &amp;c. that Mr <hi>L.</hi> preſented himſelf an Ideo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (inſtead of an Artiſt) to the World, in his botching, bungling Predictions? That he muſt thus traduce their skill, and impeach their Reputation in Aſtrology, as if they were as very ignorants therein as himſelf.</p>
               <p>But Mr <hi>L.</hi> having proved himſelf a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Ignorant in the Art he profeſſeth, by his unclerklike and unwarrantable Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, (and <hi>ſeeing R.L. P. gone, and his Northern Lion Rampant going,</hi>) is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as much as in him lies, to down with <hi>Aſtrology</hi> alſo, that the <hi>honest Aſtrologers</hi> themſelves may fall likewiſe: Whoſe ruine and deſtruction it is plain he thirſts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123655:8"/>after, for their preſuming to detect him and his Ignorance, he being (it ſeems) capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated by that Ranting and Tyrannical Principle, deſcribed by the Poet,—
<q>
                     <hi>Pereant amici, dummodo una &amp; inimici pereant.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He cares not though Friends ruin'd bee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So Enemies bear them company.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He casts dirt in the face of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy alſo: for if by the Aphoriſms and Rules thereof, others were enabled to predict thoſe Changes ſpoken of, then is not Aſtrology ſo incapacious or deficient, as Mr</hi> L. <hi>here renders it, but by the Rules thereof other perſons</hi> (viz. <hi>thoſe ſeverall men before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) were enabled to predict thoſe Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. But Mr <hi>L.</hi> ſeeing plainly enough his own Reputation begin to ſink, and his Writings every where hiſſed off the Stage with diſparagement, <hi>is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to fall alone, but would fain give A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrology its fatall blow, that both might periſh together.</hi> Not unlike the <hi>Devill,</hi> or <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> mentioned in the Revelations, who not well pleaſed to tumble headlong from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123655:9"/>Heaven ſingly, drew down a third part of the Stars with him. But how will Mr <hi>L.</hi> excuſe his Gypſie-like Jugling (to ſay no worſe of it) to the <hi>King of Sweden?</hi> Or, hath he promiſed him victory over the <hi>riſing King of Denmarke</hi> by an Art more certain and indubitable than he believes Aſtrologie? If ſo be he hath ſo done, <hi>he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſuffer a cloud of ſorrow to paſs over his brazen brow, and Vermilion to diſtain his ſhameleſs cheeks, to hear of the ſucceſs that hath anſwered his ſpurious preſages.</hi> But of this more anon.</p>
               <p>I proceed to ſome other paſſages. M.<hi>L.</hi> is now come to Apologize more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and endeavours to excuſe himſelf for flattering <hi>R.L.P.</hi> thus— <hi>Obſerving</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, <hi>by conſent of the Council of State, and Officers of the Army, owned Protector— And ſeeing him courted by Embaſſadours and Agents in</hi> October, <hi>at what time we were writing our monthly Obſervations, for we write thoſe first, in regard that the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meris and Table of Houſes are difficult to Print, ſo that nothing ſeriouſly (as we ought to have done) we laid it as a poſitive foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation (without obſerving the</hi> punctum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris <hi>of his firſt admittance, or birth,</hi> &amp;c.)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123655:9"/>Theſe are the wiſe words of <hi>William Lilly:</hi> Now, let but the Ingenious Reader behold the notable Non-ſenſe and unconnexed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them; and if he can (after a due and impartiall ſcanning thereof) make ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head or tayl, truth or ſence of them, I ſhall not in the leaſt envy his happineſs; but I muſt proteſt impartially my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them. I have pointed them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, and truly related them, as I find them in his Book, that he may not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Abuſe, or miſ-repreſentation.</p>
               <p>But to run them over a little,—I would demand of Mr <hi>L.</hi> what ſtead this Apology ſtands him in, if I ſhould admit he means ſomething by it? What is it to us, or to the wiping off the ignorance and impoſturiſm that ſticks and clings as cloſe as a Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to him, to ſay — <hi>That he writes his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemeris and table of Houſes first?</hi> As if the World were any thing concerned which part of his fooleries firſt pollute the Preſs: but were there any kind or colour of excuſe in this ſilly conceit, it is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs a meer forgery. — <hi>For he writes neither the Ephemeris, nor Tables of Houſes himſelf; but honeſt</hi> J. Sponge <hi>tranſcribes the Ephemeris for him, and the Table of Houſes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123655:10"/>hath been ſtanding (ready compoſed) this ten years and upwards at Mrs</hi> Brudenels <hi>within Newgate;</hi> ſo that the edge of this pitifull Apology is perfectly blunted, and the difficulty of his Table of Houſes to Print, clearly invalidated. (2.) I would demand of <hi>Lilly</hi> what he means by this ſtrange Parentheſis — <hi>(as we ought to have done)</hi> — for it hath no manner of relation, nor is any way kin unto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; unleſs we ſhall adjoyn it to — <hi>So that nothing ſeriouſly</hi> — This way, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, although we cannot make ſence of it, we may Truth— For <hi>Lilly</hi> in his Almanack hath done nothing ſeriouſly, or like an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, as he ought to have done. So that you ſee he is catch'd with a truth before he is aware.
<q>
                     <hi>Saepe quod inſipiens finxerat eſſe, fuit.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VVhat for a time this fellow fain'd to be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He's prov'd at last ſo in reality.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Or, if his — <hi>ſo that nothing ſeriouſly,</hi> &amp;c. can bear any other interpretation, it muſt be this — That he writes altogether in jeſt! (3.) I would fain be informed by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123655:10"/>Mr <hi>L.</hi> what he intends his Reader ſhould underſtand by theſe words — <hi>We laid IT as a poſitive foundation?</hi> If the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative <hi>IT</hi> have any Antecedent, it muſt then be, either his Ephemeris, and Table of Houſes, or elſe, the Addreſſes made to <hi>Richard</hi> L.P. The Ephemeris and Tables of Houſes cannot be the Antecedent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are no foundations of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Predictions; but a time truly propoſed or known, with the figure of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſet thereunto, is the true Radix of them. Nor can the Addreſſes to R.L.P. &amp;c. be the Antecedent, unleſs we conclude, that <hi>Lilly</hi> writes altogether by Gheſs: It muſt therefore follow, — That <hi>Lilly</hi> is guilty of groſs Non-ſence in the paſſage urged before us. Thus we ſee that <hi>Lilly,</hi> by endeavouring to excuſe himſelf, contracts greater Errors; making his writings the only pattern of <hi>Penelope's</hi> Web: Juſt as if he were either beſides himſelf, or haunted with that evill Spirit mentioned by the Poer.—
<q>
                     <hi>Diruit, aedificat, mutat quadrata rotundis.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He puls all down, he ſets up all again,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Squares for rounds are changed in his brain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:123655:11"/>A little after Mr <hi>L.</hi> comes to confeſſion in earneſt, and thinks he explains himſelf to purpoſe, when he acknowledgeth,—<hi>Our too much credulity upon the many addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, — led us into an errour.</hi> Did it ſo? Do you not therefore deſerve to be laſhed for the ſame? What had you to do to mind the Addreſſes? You pretend to Aſtrology: Unleſs by this you implicitely confeſs your ſelf a States-Mountebanke, and one that Quacks under pretence thereof; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your ſelf thereby to be (as in truth you are) only the Aſtrological News-monger. May not any man, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant in Aſtrology, predict prejudice or happineſs to Protectors, Kings, and Nations, as well as wiſe <hi>VVilliam Lilly,</hi> that gheſſes thereat (as he confeſſes to have done) by the Addreſſes and Complexions of the times? Is this to be the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full propagator of an Art? Or, an Eagle in Chriſtian Aſtrology? Is it not rather to be an Impudent-ignorant Quack? Oh, the ſordid Ignorance and quackiſm of <hi>VVilliam Lilly!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After he hath made himſelf thus ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as you have heard; to prove himſelf (yet) more ſottiſh and vain, he cracks of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123655:11"/>his predicting the change of Government in <hi>England</hi> to ſome of the Protectors friends privately: telling them, that the Government was too heavy for his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. — And then makes an Appeal to the Court of Equity in the indifferent Reader, (concluding himſelf caſt at the Common Law of Sence and Reaſon). <hi>VVhether, if he had diſcovered his diſſolution, it had been either wiſdome or diſcretion to have been publikely free in his Judgement unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector or the World,</hi> &amp;c. To which I anſwer:</p>
               <p>If you had known any thing thereof, it had been your duty to have acquainted the World therewith; or elſe to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or under what pretence, do you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the World with your Spurious Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? Beſides, <hi>VVilliam Lilly,</hi> if my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fail me not, you were of another opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when you ignorantly ſcribled againſt Captain <hi>George VVharton;</hi> the Example of <hi>Gauricus</hi> could no way ſtartle your ſtubborn ſpirit then, although you hope to creep out at that hole now. But why not tell the Protector, or the world thereof, as well as ſome of his private friends, I pray Sir? Surely, ſurely, Mr <hi>Merlin,</hi> if you had had but the leaſt knowledge or informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123655:12"/>of the downfall of <hi>Richard,</hi> you would have preſented him (as you did the long Parliament in 1652. when you were truly told what the Souldiery would do with them) with an Epiſtle, thereby premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing him of what he ſhould expect: And made the world to have heard of the Change from your Paraſitical Pen, <hi>Battus</hi>-like, on both ſides;
<q>
                     <l>— <hi>Sub illis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Montibus, inquit, erant, &amp; erant ſub monti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus illis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By yonder Mountains were thy Kine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Kine by yonder Mountains were.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Yea, and although you had received the ſame, as you did the news of the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments diſſolution, you would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have read poor <hi>Richard's</hi> down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall in the book of Heaven, as then you did theirs. But neither theſe confident Cracks, nor yet the two firſt ſheets you as vainly refer us to, as tattle or boaſt of, your ſelf, do any way make it appear that you had the leaſt knowledge thereof, by infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or that you underſtood ſo much of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123655:12"/>Art as to direct you thereunto: Only you boaſt and brag of things that are not, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping by ſuch ſilly ſhifts and ſleights to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem your (near) ſhipwrack'd Reputation. And it is every way as unlikely, and ſtrange to the truth — That <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhould acquaint any of his (that is, <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards</hi>) private friends therewith; for he durſt not lay or adventure a wager thereof himſelf with a Gentleman that deſired the ſame of him, for ſatisfaction in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Oh! <hi>William, William,</hi> all the world are not ſuch Ideots, as to be wrought upon ſo eaſily, as <hi>A Chalk-Jury.</hi> But ſuppoſe we ſhould admit that you had known any thing thereof, and had ſaid ſomething of it in your two firſt ſheets, (which were an affront to ſence to conclude:) I would then fain know, how you came to repent for your folly and ignorance therein? Surely, Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> the morning before he writ this Epiſtle, made ſome ſuch like ſupplication at the Altar of the Goddeſs <hi>Laverna</hi>— as this—
<q>
                     <l>— <hi>Pulchra Laverna,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Da mihi fallere, da juſtum ſanctum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> videri,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Noctem peccatis, &amp; fraudibus objice nubem?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:123655:13"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Goddeſs moſt fair! this ſute deny me not,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That quack and lye I may, and yet be thought</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Perſon just: my knaviſh frauds oreſpread</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ſable-clouds, that they may ne'r be read.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Certainly, <hi>William Lilly,</hi> your great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons cannot but ſhake their heads at you, when they ſeriouſly conſider what a ſilly Jack-daw, inſtead of Eagle, they have for many years protected. Would any man think, by theſe your contradictions and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norances, that you were the Perſon, whoſe Pen formerly was accounted of equall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to a Regiment of Horſe? May we not more rationally believe rather, that a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot may prove as good an Aſtrologer as ſimple <hi>W. Lilly?</hi> Oh! but <hi>William</hi> was mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of his Commitment in 1652. where he lay 13. daies together, labouring to be bayled (in no ſad condition ſure, for he was feaſted at Serjeant <hi>Birkhead's</hi> Table all that time, and paid no fees at laſt) and what was his fault forſooth! he ſaid in effect, <hi>that the Parliament ſtood upon a tottering foundation, and that the Army would diſſolve them.</hi> By which words he would needs inſinuate himſelf to have been a <hi>Quondam</hi> true Prophet in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123655:13"/>But I pray, M. <hi>Merlin,</hi> deal fairly with the world, and then tell them truly, That your commitment was not for what you ſaid in effect, but for the ſawcineſs which you uſed plainly to that Power you had a protection from, and a <hi>quondam</hi> Salary too; as I have heard your ſelf confeſs. But <hi>Lilly</hi> was then in hopes of a better Maſter of old <hi>Oliver;</hi> therefore (when every man elſe as well as he, ſaw plainly that the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery would diſſolve the Parliament) out peeps wiſe <hi>William</hi> like a Poſitical Paraſite, and pretends Aſtrologically to predict it. An admirable Piece of Art to be boaſted of!</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And is not he, a Quackist ſingular,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When things are done, that reads them in his Star?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> not forgetting his uſual can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting clawing humour, is come to flatter the preſent Power; and in his Quacking-ſtrain, pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ends to demonſtrate the Armies Declarations ſatisfactory to the whole Engliſh Nation; and mentions ſome of the heads thereof, the better to inſinuate himſelf into their Favours and Affections. For <hi>Lilly</hi> cannot fill an Almanack of ſix
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123655:14"/>ſheets of Paper, (although he have three of them done to his hand, as I have before proved) without relating a packet of News. But <hi>Lilly!</hi> I would fain know what you have to do with any thing of News, or the humour of the times at all? Doth <hi>Guido Bonatus, Haly, Junctine, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, Ptolomy,</hi> or any other Aſtrologer war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any ſuch courſe? I am confident, Mr. <hi>Merlin,</hi> they do not: and you prove your ſelf but an impudent indigent Quack in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, and make that alſo to be looked upon, but as a higher degree of <hi>Lieger-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> by doing it. But Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> goes on, ſaying, <hi>That no mortal man could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that</hi> R. <hi>L. P. ſhould have loſt his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without one or two broken heads.</hi> But I beſeech you, Sir, what is this to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, whether he loſt his Government by force of blood, or peaceably? I am ſure, notwithſtanding your inſulting over that modeſt Gentleman thus baſely, you your ſelf are like to looſe your Credit in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie at a far eaſier rate; and if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every thing, you cannot but ſee it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For whereas you thought to be famous in after-Ages for your skill therein, you are now like to dye baſely, ignominiouſly, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123655:14"/>un-bemoaned; and (that which is worſt of all) will always be eſteemed of, as a Quack and Impoſtor in Aſtrologie, and a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Incendiary among Nations. However, it is ſome Credit to Aſtrologie, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, (yea, and Honour alſo) to Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that this Arch-pretender is unmask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſcovered in his life time, to be what he is; and that he dare not, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, anſwer for himſelf.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, <hi>William Lilly</hi> thinks he hath dealt by his Reader like a good Chriſtian Aſtrologer, when he ſaies, <hi>We ſolemnly profeſs our miſtake concerning</hi> R. <hi>L. P. yet it is not ſo great, as to blaſt us perpetually; if our Writings ſince</hi> 1644. <hi>be civilly peruſed by Artiſts, not Botchers.</hi> What this Addle-headed Fellow means by his <hi>civilly peruſed,</hi> I underſtand not, except it be this,—That for him to be read with applauſe, whether he deſerve it or not, is to be <hi>civilly peruſed:</hi> or to read him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking Cognizance of his Ignorance; or if we take notice thereof, yet not to tell the world of it: this ſurely is to <hi>read him civilly.</hi> But Sir I although I have avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all theſe Paraſitical ways, (which, as your Trade is to flatter, ſo you love to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123655:15"/>flattered, yet) <hi>I have civilly peruſed all your writings ſince</hi> 1644. (<hi>i. e.</hi> I was not, I dare aver, ſo drunk with Wine, when I read them, as you with Ignorance, when you writ them:) and really, I find them every way ſo empty and idle, that it is a ſhame for any but <hi>William Lilly</hi> to own them. But to particularize ſome of them:—Take from your <hi>Introduction</hi> (which is the beſt you dare to boaſt of) what you have ſtolen from <hi>Haly, Origanus,</hi> and <hi>Albubater,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing their better names, to make the world eſteem it yours; and then it will prove the exact Emblem of your ignorant ſelf. As for Example: Who but a <hi>Botcher in Art,</hi> would have printed a <hi>Nativity with Directions no leſs then ſeven or eight years falſe;</hi> as you have done the <hi>Moons</hi> in your <hi>Introduction?</hi> Or would any but a Novice in Aſtrologie have given the <hi>Sun,</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heaven</hi> two different Right Aſcentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, as you have? And is not he a <hi>ſilly Stit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and moſt <hi>notorious Botcher in Art,</hi> that knows not <hi>Apogeon,</hi> from <hi>Perigeon?</hi> Theſe with a hundred more, are to be found in <hi>Lillies Introduction.</hi> And all his other Pamphlets are exactly of the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:123655:15"/>
                  <hi>Nec lac lacti; nec ovum ova ſimilius.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twixt Milk and Milk, the likeneſs is not greater;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor Egge to Egge, more parallel in feature.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>And as they may call each other <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> by reaſon of their exact ſimilitudes; ſo they may truly call him <hi>Dad,</hi> it being impoſſible for them to be begotten by any other. But <hi>è diverticulo viam.</hi> I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his ſolemn profeſſion concerning <hi>Richard</hi> L. P.</p>
               <p>Since you are come to the Stool of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, (though moſt unwillingly) why do not you (to make but one work of all) ſolemnly profeſs all your other miſtakes, which are at large charged upon you in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; or, <hi>Spurious Prognoſticator,</hi> and in the <hi>King of Swedes Nativity?</hi> This you ought to have done, if you had any hopes of being received into mercy, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to eſcape <hi>blaſting perpetually.</hi> Can the <hi>accurſed Murtherer,</hi> any way <hi>reaſonably</hi> hope to be reprieved from the Gallows, by confeſſing a petty Fact of Theft he hath committed? Sir! it is not your acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123655:16"/>your Errour concerning <hi>R.</hi> L. P. that any way excuſes you from the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Crime of betraying the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> under pretence of telling him, you read what you writ for him, in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: Neither doth this ſimple Blind, you caſt before the eyes of the world, any ways protect your ignorance all along in Art; <hi>viz.</hi> in ſetting Figures forty one minutes of time falſe; and in raiſing your Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Judgements (under pretence of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to Art) upon ſuch deformed and erronious foundations. Nor is it leſs then an ignorant and effeminate ſleight, and juggle of you, to inſinuate to the world <hi>that your Antagoniſts are Botchers, not Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists.</hi> If they are <hi>Botchers in Art,</hi> is it not the eaſier work for you to anſwer them? And would it not more and better become you to invalidate their skill there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and weaken their many charges againſt you, then for to rail thus upon either their Perſons or Parts? Or, are they Botchers in Art becauſe they write againſt ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a Work-man as they have proved you to be? Surely, ſurely, <hi>Lilly,</hi> it is more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then your knowledge in Aſtrologie, that you have proved your ſelf a Botcher
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123655:16"/>and Bungler alſo, in the Art you pretend to ſteer the Affairs of Kings and Kingdomes by, in not vindicating your own Repute, but ſuffering it to be trampled upon at pleaſure; even by the ignorant ſort, as well as the ingenious and skillful. The Tongue of each Child, is now become a Trumpet of <hi>William Lillies</hi> ignorance.</p>
               <p>But <hi>wiſe William Lilly</hi> comes here, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply endeavouring to anſwer that which is urged againſt him concerning the <hi>Swedes,</hi> thus: —<hi>We were not obliged to give an account of any thing which might prejudice him; (the Swede) or give encouragement to his many enemies.</hi> And why not, I pray Sir? Were you bribed to ſecrecy, that you might the better betray him, by puffing him up with falſe hopes? Or did you flatter him with the weak Winde of your Cathedral Cunning; thinking thereby his Enemies were ſo Puſillanimous as to be affrighted at your Quacking Skill? If the firſt, have you not ſhewn your ſelf a plain <hi>Ambo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dexter?</hi> If the latter, what Ideot (beſides <hi>Merlinus Anglicus</hi>) would have been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo groſs a piece of Pride? But that you may adjudge <hi>Lilly</hi> to be in earneſt, he interrogates—<hi>Is</hi> Pomerania <hi>quite loſt?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123655:17"/>or is he beaten out of</hi> Pruſſia? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And behold! at the ſame time that he wrote thoſe Boaſts and Cracks, (as if Providence intended to ſtigmatize him for a notorious Lyar) the K. of <hi>Swedes</hi> leaves his Leaguer, and flees to <hi>Cronenburgh</hi> Caſtle, having loſt all his Army in <hi>Fuenen.</hi> Which News is ſtill freſh in memory, and cannot but make <hi>Lillies</hi> Ears to tingle, and Cheeks to bluſh, unleſs he hath ſold himſelf an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Vaſſal to Impudence and Quackiſm. But <hi>Lilly</hi> like a Lyar of the firſt Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, goes on, interrogating further: <hi>Is not the King of</hi> Swede <hi>still strongly encamped before</hi> Copenhagen? <hi>which City we hope God will give him.</hi> Indeed, Mr. <hi>L</hi> he is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> but in <hi>Cronenburgh,</hi> poſſibly blocked up himſelf by this time: And what reaſon (I pray) had you to hope God would give him <hi>Copenhagen?</hi> None in Aſtrologie, I am ſure; although you ignorantly report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it ſhould be taken in <hi>Novem.</hi> 1658. Beſides, hath it not been in print reſolved according to the Rules of Art, that the K. of <hi>Swede</hi> ſhall never gain <hi>Copenhagen?</hi> You ſhould have rendered the Author of that, a perſon miſtaken, or a Botcher in Art (as you ſay all your Antagoniſts are) before
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123655:17"/>you had promoted your own ſimple hopes in the room of Aſtrology; which if you know any thing therein, you cannot but confeſs plainly, denies <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any part of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Territories, to be long curbed by the King of <hi>Swede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, but what of all this? ſaith this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſite, <hi>the King of</hi> Swedes <hi>condition is not ſo bad as rendred by ſome ſtitching Pens.</hi> If by ſtitching Pens he mean the Pen of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Verax</hi> for one, who hath publiſhed this Princes Nativity, I ſhall tell him, that that Perſon hath ſo Art-like whipt and ſtitcht him up, that he appears to the world a meer bundle or lump of Nonſence and flattery, inſtead of an Artiſt. And hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed given that King more and better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe for nothing (as is to be ſeen by the Book, to be ſold at <hi>William Larnar's</hi> upon <hi>Ludgate Hill</hi>) touching his preſent affairs, than ever <hi>Lilly</hi> did, or indeed was able to do, for the Gold Chain he received from him. And he hath ſhewn more Art, and done Aſtrology greater honour, in that ſmall Tract, than <hi>Lilly</hi> ever did in all his Idle and Addle Stories, which he nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names his works, ſince 1644. But if by ſtitching Pens, he means ſome Taylors
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123655:18"/>Pens, that have been active to diſcover his ignorance in Art; Is it not a ſhame that he can anſwer for himſelf no better? But were there any ſuch thing, doth not <hi>Lilly</hi> appear to be an Impudent, Proud, Pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, Domineering fellow, ſo to forget his own Original as to complain of ſtitching Pens? What was <hi>Lilly</hi> at firſt himſelf? was he not a Taylors boy, <hi>viz.</hi> an Apprentice to old <hi>Pawlin</hi> in the <hi>Strand?</hi> Ask the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-men that ply at <hi>Strand-bridge,</hi> and they will affirm it: Or if you are loath to take that pains, read Captain <hi>Wharton's Merlini Anglici Errata;</hi> who proves him not only a Taylor, but a womans-taylor, in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he might perhaps have proved a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Aſtrologer for Queen <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> than <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Come <hi>William Lilly,</hi> I would have you hereafter to knit your knots better in Aſtrology, to prevent the being marked for an Ideot therein by ſtitching Pens; that is, to keep your ſelf within compaſs, and not give ſuch large opportunities to men of your own Trade to ſtitch you up, as you have done. And do not hereafter bewray your own Neſt; for had not your own Pen been the Index of your Pride and Folly, the world
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123655:18"/>had willingly rocked your Taylorſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep; and were indifferently well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that you ſhould paſs for a Quack in Aſtrology among them, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had to the Botching you prove your ſelf guilty of, in tranſlating <hi>Ptolomies A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſmes.</hi> But <hi>William, William,</hi> if you are ſo Lord-like grown, as to forget the ſtayers of your Taylorſhip, by which you have cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (as you think) to your Eagleſhip in Aſtrology, can you be angry, if thoſe whom you (ſcurrilouſly) term botchers, (not Artiſts) in a juſt recompence, preſs down the Plumes of your Pride with your own Taylors Gooſe? Oh, <hi>William, William,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Talion's</hi> Law.</p>
               <p>But Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> telleth us, <hi>he writes this year in great perplexity of ſpirit.</hi> I am content to believe you Mr <hi>Lilly;</hi> It appeareth ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, by what you have preſented us with! And what either Art or ſence can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from a diſtempered man?</p>
               <p>To conclude his Epiſtle, he ſaies— <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will expect that he ſhould ſay ſomething touching the Northern Quarrel.</hi> Do they ſo Sir! Who are thoſe many you mean, I wonder? I am certain they cannot be of the number of the Learned and Ingenious.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123655:19"/>But 'tis no matter; be they who they will this I can tell them, they are like to looſe their longing: for <hi>Lilly</hi> hath not yet had intelligence ſufficient to officiate their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. And that which is more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he is not engaged (yet) to Pimp for either of thoſe two able Engliſh Generals, as he flatteringly ſtiles them, in hopes (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) he may be entertained to Quack for one of them under pretence of Aſtrology. But I ſhall adviſe them both, rather to implore the Duſt of Mother <hi>Shipton</hi> for Counſell, than either the Addle Pate, or Yeilding Pen of this Proditorious Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. And ſo I paſs from his Epiſtle to his Book, which the ingenious Reader, as well as I, ſhall find as empty and void of Art, as this his Epiſtle is of good Apology, Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, Sence, or Learning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. <hi>His Generall Judgements examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>L.</hi> being a little entred into his General Judgments, lets glide from his Pen a truth before he is aware—telling us — <hi>That he will deliver his WEAK
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123655:19"/>CONCEPTIONS upon the two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſes, which hapned in</hi> October, <hi>and</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, 1659. Certainly Sir, you are not in earneſt now; you were wont to ſet a better value upon your own Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. What? Is our Eagle-like-skill in Aſtrology, and our deep knowledge in the Doctrine of Angels, and our ſharp under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Theurgie and the Chriſtall, all on a ſudden departed! Never a <hi>Dick-Mye</hi> left to ſtrengthen us? Nothing left us but weak Conceptions? This is hard indeed! but poſſibly Sir! by this your humble ſtile, you expect that others ſhould deem your Conceptions ſtrenuous; which <hi>(Sine dubio)</hi> they will have little reaſon to do, when they have once read you over. But by the Complexion and Temperature of your Conceptions, we ſhall (I hope) ere we make an end, be able to paſs a Judgement upon their weakneſs, or worth.</p>
               <p>To proceed — Mr <hi>L.</hi> tels us—<hi>That the Lunar Eclipſe on</hi> Octob. 19. <hi>portends, that as</hi> Venus, <hi>Ruler of it, leaves her own houſe for a worſe, approaching</hi> Saturn's <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; ſo near theſe Months</hi> (he names none, unleſs we muſt underſtand <hi>October</hi> in the Plurall!) <hi>do many unhappy perſons (made
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123655:20"/>ſo) either by an uncomfortable Miniſtry, or the Rigor of the Law of Nations, leave good and large poſſeſſions,</hi> &amp;c. Why <hi>Venus</hi> her propinquity to <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhould undoe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by Miniſters, either comfortable or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable, I underſtand not; neither doth Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> I ſuppoſe; for his Art takes no knowledge of any ſuch thing; what his diſaffection to the Miniſtry may, I trouble not my ſelf to enquire. But that he may diſcover his unparallel'd hatred to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, he runs over his old ſong again in a higher ſtrain, thus, — <hi>As</hi> Venus <hi>is haſtening to a Conjunction of</hi> Saturn, <hi>he much queſtions whether the meer illiterate man will not get ground of many of thoſe LAZY MEN, whom we call Goſpell-Ministers, Church-Divines, or Preaching Divines.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Venus</hi> (as I ſaid before) and <hi>Saturn</hi> have nothing to do with the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> yet <hi>Lilly</hi> (the better to ſpit his venome at the perſons of that Sacred Order) wreſts his Art from the true meaning thereof, to bring that within the verge of his Sawcy Pen. But the main reaſon why this Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous-inſolent-fellow cannot Print a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Pamphlet without diſhonouring that Heavenly Function, is, becauſe the Moon
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123655:20"/>is in ſquare to <hi>Jupiter</hi> in his <hi>Swiniſh Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture.</hi> But pray Sir! What is the reaſon that you tell us not when this Eclipſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins and ends by your Calculation; that we may ſee what reaſon you have (by the figure thereof) to predict at ſo malicious a rate of Miniſters? but you (I preſume) underſtand the Doctrine of Eclipſes, and that of Angels, a like.</p>
               <p>But why <hi>Lazy men, which we have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Goſpell-Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c? Really, I judge it impoſſible for any of them you mean to be ſo lazy in Divinity as you are in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. And why (I pray) <hi>ſuch as we have called Goſpell-Miniſters?</hi> &amp;c. Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them to be perſons not deſerving that Title? Or, are you turn'd Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt or Quaker all of a ſudden, that you thus grudgingly give them the Epithets that are their proper due? But your love and affection to the Miniſtry, is ſufficiently known; your ſcurrilous Pen hath been the Conveyer of your Gall towards them for many years together. Which very thing ſhould, me thinks, make you more civill toward your Antagoniſts (or your ſelf ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) than to brand them as Ranters and Atheiſts; when you cannot but be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123655:21"/>that there are none ſuch notorious Ranters and Atheiſts as thoſe that ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly abuſe God's deareſt Meſſengers. But <hi>Lillie's Religion</hi> and <hi>Aſtrology</hi> are known to be of a ſtamp.</p>
               <p>After many Tautologies and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies, <hi>Lilly</hi> is paſſed from the Moons Eclipſe to that of the Sun, on <hi>Novemb.</hi> 4. but gives us neither the time of beginning or end; only preſents us with the middle, and duration, and Digits eclipſed, though not truly. <hi>The middle</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is at</hi> 9. <hi>min. paſt</hi> 3. <hi>in the Evening.</hi> But he is ſtrangely out in this; for Mr <hi>Wing</hi> hath calculated it, and my ſelf hath proved it, the middle thereof was at 4. min. 30. ſec. paſt 3. So that obſerve what difference there is between 4. min. 30. ſec. and 9. min. for ſo much is M. <hi>L.</hi> diſtant from the truth. The Duration, he falſely ſaith, was 2. h. 3. m. But the true Duration was 2. h. 21. m. 19. ſec. as is demonſtable by <hi>Aſtron. Inſtaur.</hi> So that Mr <hi>Lilly</hi> is no leſs than 18. mi. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the truth in this alſo. <hi>Then he ſaith the Digits eclipſed were</hi> 7. <hi>deg.</hi> 32. <hi>ſec.</hi> but the true Digits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> eclipſed, were 8. deg. 48. min. 1. ſec. So that ignorant <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lilly</hi> is out no leſs than one whole
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123655:21"/>digit, 47 <hi>min.</hi> 29 <hi>ſec.</hi> in the quantity of the Eclipſe. Now from all theſe Errors in Calculation, is not <hi>Lilly</hi> likely to make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Predictions? <hi>But as are his Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſo are his Judgements, without either Art or Order.</hi> Nevertheleſs, <hi>hence</hi> Lilly <hi>can take opportunity to abuſe</hi> Scorpio, <hi>and call it a rugged treacherous, violent Signe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſo by all wiſe men.</hi> But, I pray <hi>Sir!</hi> how prove you that? except you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, what your ſelf agrees to, <hi>all wiſe men muſt needs conſent to.</hi> Certainly, Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> you cannot have ſo ſhort a head, as to think that the fortieth part of wiſe men under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any thing at all of <hi>Scorpio.</hi> And I ſuppoſe you would not be ſo underſtood, as to cenſure all men for Fools, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nothing thereof. This therefore muſt paſs for one of your wooden <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(i.e.) ranting boasts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why, I intreat you, Sir, is</hi> Scorpio <hi>grown ſo odious in your eyes?</hi> Is it becauſe <hi>Saturn</hi> is therein, in your Nativity, and in Oppoſition to your <hi>Sol?</hi> Or is it becauſe you have an ignorant (undeſerved) hatred to any, that have it Horoſcopical at Birth? If ſo, were I a <hi>Scorpioniſt,</hi> I ſhould tell you, You have foamed out your filth in ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123655:22"/>and abuſing a noble, fixed, immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Signe of the Zodiack, as violent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whiſe you are compelled to draw your poiſonous breath under a more treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, diſſembling, and double-bodied ſigne of your own, <hi>viz. Piſces;</hi> perhaps a main reaſon of your forked tongue and actions. <hi>Scorpio ſcorns the ignorant, cold, effeminate, reaſonleſs Evaſions, and low-orbed ſilly come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>off's, of</hi> Piſces; and that galls mutable, and turn-about <hi>William Lilly,</hi> ſo that he muſt needs wreak his weak and worthleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in Print againſt it.</p>
               <p>But what will <hi>Lilly</hi> ſay, if I prove he hath beſpattered <hi>Piſces</hi> in as baſe a manner as he hath <hi>Scorpio?</hi> and that in this very Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack of his too? Will he not confeſs himſelf more rigling and uncertain in his Judgement than an Eele? Let him be pleaſed to peruſe what in page two he hath written, <hi>viz. — When the Angles of the Figure of any Eclipſe are of double-bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed Signes, as thoſe of the Lunar defect are, the Councels of the then times are uncertain, various and mutable, treacherous, carryed on with abundance of Fraud, Violence and Jugling, &amp;c.</hi> But perhaps <hi>Lilly</hi> will ſay,— Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Piſces</hi> is no double-bodied Signe:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123655:22"/>Indeed it is no matter what he ſaies; for by this notorious Contradiction, <hi>We may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate his Conſcience to be as large, as his Pen liberal.</hi> But paſſing theſe things, let us hear him in his Pontificalibus of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, threatning the poor City of <hi>London:</hi> Mars <hi>in</hi> Gemini, <hi>gives us great cauſe to fear</hi> LONDON <hi>will be the place, and Plague or Peſtilence the devouring Diſeaſe,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>God defend it from more,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for it was here, here, here, that — and it muſt be here, here, here, that—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What this Frenzie-Fellow ſhould mean by his three Couple of HERES, unleſs it ſhould be <hi>to hear an ignorant Quack ſimply prate,</hi> I underſtand not. Is it not a ſigne by this, that he writes not onely in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of ſpirit, as he complains of, but in diſtraction of minde alſo? Howbeit, he can (in this diſtracted temper) ignorantly threaten <hi>London</hi> with a Plague, although Aſtrologie doth not (yet) this three years. He hath indeed done ſo ten years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and miſſed; poſſibly he may hit it at laſt; if the <hi>M.C.</hi> ad <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> 
                  <hi>Saiurn &amp; Solis</hi> give him leave to preſent himſelf a ſcribbling Fool in print to the world a little longer.</p>
               <p>But he advances, ſaying, — <hi>The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123655:23"/>Clergie run high, — and ſtir up Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults: a thing very frequent with men of that Order, theſe ſix or ſevenſcore years last paſt; yea, in all ages,</hi> &amp;c. Still you ſee this Fellow muſt be abuſing the Miniſtry, and make that the main burthen of his bung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Predictions. Had his Antagoniſt been guilty of any ſuch Crime, he muſt have been rendered a <hi>Ranter, Atheiſt,</hi> and what not? And doth <hi>Lilly</hi> think that we ſhall eſteem him any other then a Ranting-raving A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, that thus beſpatters thoſe worthy Lights of the Church, that conſtantly ſpend their Lamps of Life, to diſpel the dark Clouds of Ignorance, that ſuch Atheiſts and Scoffers endeavour to bring upon the Sun of our Religion? Or can he take him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be leſs then a perſon of a foul ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Soul, that thus licentiouſly traduces the whole Body of Chriſts Miniſtry with the Poyſon of his polluted Pen? But he thinks he can come off from all this, by colloguing thus: — <hi>Still we retain all Civility both in Heart and Soul for the godly Miniſters.</hi> Here you may behold the true Emblem of this Hypocrites diſſembling Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent, <hi>viz. Piſces.</hi> Firſt, he moſt baſely and undeſervedly abuſes the whole Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:123655:23"/>and exhibits an impious and unjuſt Charge againſt them, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſix or ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years long; nay, as long as the age of the world; and almoſt in the ſame breath, — <hi>He retains all Civility of Heart for them.</hi> Oh, the notorious Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Diſſimulation of this Cloven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Fellow! If this be your Civility, pray Sir, let me partake of your Moroſity.</p>
               <p>To render himſelf as weak in parts, as hypocritical and diſſembling in Spirit, in the ſame Page he writes thus: — <hi>But if he ſhall judge according to the genuine Rules of the MORE P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RER Aſtrologie,</hi> &amp;c. Can Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> tell (I wonder) what himſelf means <hi>by the Rules of the MORE PU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RER Aſtrologie?</hi> Had that Perſon whom Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſo wiſely terms <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> or <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Impudent Fool,</hi> been guilty of jumbling Comparatives (unlawfully) thus together, we ſhould have heard of him in ſome ſuch like Language:—<hi>Behold the ignorance of this impudent ranting Boy, that cannot write ſence! a ridiculous Fool, that hath need to go to School again; and not preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the world in print, until he underſtand true Engliſh!</hi> All which Epithets, I ſhall in modeſty ſpare Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> becauſe he is, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123655:24"/>
                  <hi>viridi Senectute,</hi> his green old age. Yet nevertheleſs I may be bold to tell the world, — That by this paſſage of his <hi>MORE PURER,</hi> it appears, he underſtands true Engliſh, as much as he doth Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and no more. And ſo I paſs his idle Diſcourſe of Eclipſes, and come to his Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Figure. Which he ſet to 6 <hi>h.</hi> 9 <hi>m. p. m. March</hi> 9. but by his own Ephemeris is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly falſe. Examine it thus elſe.—
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>March</hi> 1660. 9. <hi>D.</hi> ☉'s place. ♓ 29 <hi>d.</hi> 43 <hi>m.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>March</hi> 1660. 10. <hi>D.</hi> ☉'s place. ♈ 0 <hi>d.</hi> 42. <hi>m.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Difference in Longit. 0. <hi>d.</hi> 59 <hi>m.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Diſtance of ☉ from firſt point of ♈, 17 <hi>m.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore I work by this Rule:—If 59 <hi>m.</hi> give 24 <hi>h.</hi> what ſhall 17 <hi>m.</hi> give? <hi>Facit</hi> 6 <hi>h.</hi> 54 <hi>m.</hi> So that Mr. <hi>L.</hi> is out no leſs then 45 <hi>m.</hi> in time, if we make his own Book the Judge. But the true time is at 6 <hi>h.</hi> 51 <hi>m.</hi> 24 <hi>ſec.</hi> So that had Mr. <hi>L.</hi> been true to his own Ephemerides, I ſhould have ſpared him here. But I admire how <hi>Lilly</hi> ſtumbled ſo near upon the truth in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemeris, and yet his Figure ſo falſe. Surely he hath been pilfering from <hi>V. Wing,</hi> for reduce <hi>Eichſtade</hi> he cannot, unleſs Mr. <hi>Sponge</hi> help him. But 'tis no matter, be his Figures true or falſe, he proceeds to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,—and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123655:24"/>tells us, Libra <hi>aſcends, and the Significatrix of the people</hi> (which muſt be <hi>Venus,</hi> if the Aſcendent ſignifie them) <hi>is well dignified, and in Aſpect of the two Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Planets,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>Venus</hi> Sir, is in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment; and by your Figure in <hi>Octava Domo,</hi> and beholds neither <hi>Saturn</hi> nor <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter;</hi> are not you therefore a notorious Ignorant in Art? Who is the Botcher now? Sure I am, <hi>if</hi> William Lilly <hi>underſtood his Taylors Needle no better then his Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers Pen, we may juſtly conclude him a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry botching and bungling Fellow at both.</hi> Are not thoſe Kings and States in a ſad condition, that are neceſſitated to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice about their moſt emergent Affairs, from ſo indigent a Fellow?</p>
               <p>But <hi>William Lilly</hi> hath learned to talk big, and to utter high-ſwelling words of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that the common people may believe his head is periwig'd with the Clouds; and tells us—<hi>That toward the latter end of</hi> May, <hi>or beginning of</hi> June <hi>or</hi> July (ſome time or another, 'tis no matter when) <hi>the Conglomeration of no leſs then five Planets in the Signe</hi> Scorpio, <hi>a fruitful Signe</hi> (here <hi>Scorpio</hi> is grown into favour again with this two-tongued Ideot) <hi>may juſtly import
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123655:25"/>a meeting together of many people,</hi> &amp;c. But Sir, there is no ſuch Conglomeration of the Planets in any of the moneths menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, nor in many moneths after; (what Conglomeration of Impudence, Ignorance and Folly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there may be in your brain, I know not;) your Judgement therefore is as idle, as your inſinuation falſe.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Lilly</hi> fearing ſome Change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I ſuppoſe (for you muſt know, that he would have the world believe, that <hi>Revolutions</hi> as are ſignally pointed at by his Pen, as the Viciſſitude of the Air is foretold by his rotten Carcaſe) begins to tell his Readers—<hi>That as ſome Pratlers abuſe</hi> Oliver <hi>Protector,—Thus do other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Tongues and Pens deprave even the whole line of the</hi> Stuarts <hi>Family, and call it accurſed; whilſt their own is owned more abominable.</hi> All that I ſhall return to this paſſage, is this:—That if he can finde any man in <hi>Europe</hi> that hath dealt more vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with that <hi>Family</hi> then himſelf, both in Tongue &amp; Pen, let him bring them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Laſh; if not, let him paſs under his own Cenſure, for a fellow of a viperous Tongue and Pen, and conſider what he hath written in his Monarchy, and his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123655:25"/>for the years 1649, 1650, 1651, 1652, 1653, 1654. and other his fooliſh Pamphlets: But perhaps he thinks, to write againſt an honourable Family, is not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it.</p>
               <p>So from his Vernal, <hi>I</hi> follow him to his Aeſtival Ingreſs; where he aſſerts that <hi>Sol</hi> enters <hi>Cancer, June</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> 9 <hi>h.</hi> 12 <hi>m. P. M.</hi> but this is as true as the former, as <hi>I</hi> ſhall make appear by his own Book. Which (ſetting aſide his Printers errors) <hi>I</hi> exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>June</hi> 1660. 10 ☉'s place. ♊ 29 <hi>d.</hi> 36 <hi>m.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>June</hi> 1660. 11 ☉'s place. ♋ 0. <hi>d.</hi> 33. <hi>m.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>☉'s Diurnal Motion. 0. <hi>d.</hi> 57. <hi>m.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>His diſtance from the firſt point of ♋ is 24 <hi>m</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Then <hi>I</hi> ſay, If 57 <hi>m.</hi> give 24 <hi>h.</hi> what 24 <hi>m? Facit</hi> 10 <hi>h.</hi> 6 <hi>m.</hi> So that here you ſee, he is miſtaken no leſs then 54 <hi>m.</hi> in time, as his own Book proves againſt him. <hi>Oh! Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum horrendum! An Aſtrologer, and cannot ſet a true Figure!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, Mr. <hi>L.</hi> adventures upon this Scheme alſo, to deliver his WEAK CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEPTIONS, and ſays—<hi>The Heavens do not at all ſmile upon the Actions of Kings,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:123655:26"/>Princes, Supreme Magiſtrates and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</hi> For which paſſage I ſhall account with him anon. But although Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> Aſtrologie fail him, yet his good Tutelary or Preſidentiary Angels do not ſure, whom he ſaith,—<hi>Generated that very quick Comet in</hi> 1652. (not ſo quick neither as an <hi>ignis fatuus;</hi> for it laſted a whole moneth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) <hi>as the Precurſor of ſome eminent Perſon or Perſons, or their riſing unto honor in</hi> Europe, &amp;c. Before Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to predict ought to depend upon the Influences of Comets, he ſhould have made his way clear, by removing the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block that lay in it. For <hi>I</hi> deny (and ſo doth learned <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and moſt Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts) that Comets are generated by his <q>Tutelary or Preſidentiary Angels, but are engendred of <hi>Ignean Vapors,</hi> conſiſting of a viſcous, ſulphurous, and compacted mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, attracted from the Earth by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergie of the Coeleſtial Movers, into the higheſt Region of the Air, ſometimes into the Starry Region, whence it is cloſely conglutinated into a great Lump, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the continued ſupply it hath from below: and being thus compacted, is ſet on fire in time convenient, by the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:123655:26"/>heat of the place where it reſts, and burns either long, or a little while, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the paucity or plenty of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which it conſiſts.</q> This is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the learned generally. And ſurely Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> it will be no ill-concluding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, to ſay — He that is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the Generation of Comets, muſt be ſo alſo in their effects. But Mr <hi>L.</hi> tattles of Comets, and Angels, to cover his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in Aſtrology only; he poor man! knows no more of the natures or effects of either, than the ſillieſt Potter that trots about the Streets of an Errand, or his poor Siſter (the Waſher-woman) in <hi>Milford-Lane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whether he underſtand Comets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or not, he boaſts as if he underſtood all things; and quackingly tels us, — <hi>The Auſtrian forces ſeem to be threatned near this time, either with the loſs of ſome battell, or town, &amp;c. if any thing at all he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in war or quarrel with the not conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> Swede, <hi>whoſe forces now, where in Action, will make it appear they fight for a good King, and in a good honeſt cauſe.</hi> And how comes it about that the Auſtrians muſt be thus menaced? Is it meerly upon this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:123655:27"/>grounded, if they fight againſt the not conquered Swede? But pray Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> what Rule in Aſtrology have you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Swediſh King to be good, and his Cauſe honeſt? Will you never leave your clawing Paraſiticall Practiſes? But a little further good <hi>William!</hi> If the King of Swedes be aſſured victory over the Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,—How comes it to paſs that <hi>Lilly</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted that <hi>the heavens ſmile not upon the Actions of Kings,</hi> &amp;c. as before you have heard him? Are <hi>Lillies</hi> Angels of no better uſe to him, than thus to ſuffer him to run into Errors and Contradictions? Or, hath his good Genius left him? But what will <hi>Lilly</hi> ſay, if the Swedes and Auſtrians ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver quarrell?—If they do not, then creeps he ſneakingly out at his <hi>great IF!</hi> For his Predictions depend upon <hi>ifs</hi> and <hi>ands,</hi> although the Coeleſtial Edicts do not. All his preſages are whimſical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the aire; and If the sky fals, <hi>Lilly</hi> and his Swediſh King may catch Larks together.</p>
               <p>But ſaith <hi>Lilly—The Swedes cannot be made ſubject to thoſe misfortunes, as ſome ſcribling Pens would have them.—If the Comet in</hi> 1618. <hi>did firſt appear in</hi> 25. <hi>d.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:123655:27"/>of</hi> ♏—<hi>Then we find the</hi> ☉ <hi>in that very degree at the King of Swedes birth, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:trine">△</g> ♃ <hi>in M. C. and</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                  <hi>applying to his</hi> ⚹. <hi>Remove theſe Configurations out of the Heavens, and then his enemies may rant and prate, as ſome very botchers, not workmen, impertinently have done,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But ſith either he or they are men of no quality, but Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Botchers, he or they are below our Pen to take a full Cognizance thereof, their prating or perſons</hi> — Aquila non capit Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas; <hi>we ſhould make our ſelf ridiculous to anſwer a boy, or a ranting-impudent fool, that dare not own his Name to be</hi> G.I. <hi>or</hi> I.G.</p>
               <p>If I do not prove this ambitious Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite as botching a Fellow, and of as mean Quality, and a verier Boy in Art, than him whom he ſcurrilouſly ſtiles ſo, yea, though his Preſidentiary Angels ſhould take his part;— Let <hi>William Lilly</hi> again ſay, he hath but a Boy to deal with. Firſt, his citing the Comet 1618. to favour the King of <hi>Swede,</hi> is both vain and fooliſh. And if it ſignifie any thing (It happening 4 years before he was an Embryo) it muſt be miſchief: Yea, and ſuch as thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iſts (whom this Botcher terms Scriblers) have mentioned. <hi>Ariſtotle, Pliny,</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:123655:28"/>ſay,—<hi>Comets are the Meſſengers of great Calamities, and of the death and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Kings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but never of any good to them.</hi> The Noble Hiſtorian <hi>Suetonius,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on <hi>Claudius, Cap.</hi> 26. hath theſe words — <hi>Preſagia mortis ejus precipua fuerunt exortus ſtellae crinitae, quam Cometa vocant: The Principal preſages of his death were ariſings of the hairy ſtar they call a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> But ſuppoſe I ſhould (for diſcourſe ſake) admit the Comet in 1618. to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie good to the King of <hi>Swede,</hi> becauſe his ☉ fell to be in the degree of its firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; yet his <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> happening in the oppoſite point thereof, if the one portended any good, the other muſt evill; and <hi>William Lilly</hi> ſtill appear a ſilly-ſhifting fellow, that would force that to ſpeak for Kings, that in truth hath neither heart or face to do ſo.</p>
               <p>Yea, but ſaith <hi>Lilly, the</hi> ☉ <hi>applies ad</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:trine">△</g> ♃ <hi>in M.C. and</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                  <hi>to his</hi> ⚹ <hi>alſo.</hi>—All which I grant; and <hi>Merlinus Verax</hi> hath made as much of thoſe things for the Swede, as Aſtrologically they will bear. But <hi>Lilly,</hi> you appear very partiall in not relating the Bad, as well as the Good, as he hath done: for to balance thoſe good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:123655:28"/>you mention, he tels you that ♃ is retrograde in the tenth houſe, afflicted by the corporall preſence of ♄, and both in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> ♀, Lady of his Aſcendant; and that the Luminaries are in oppoſition from cruell and molicious places of the Heavens; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the moſt pernicious Direction of <hi>M. C. ad</hi> ♂ ♄. which he now groans and labours under, whoſe effects are theſe: — <hi>Maximas indignitates &amp; odia Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum aut Magnatum judicit; vario quoque malorum genere, dignitates, officia, honores atque favores ſubvertit: Negotia cum tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate natum proficere facit, facinoroſa vero ſcelere excitat, &amp; nonnunquam mortem lata judicis ſententia portendit.</hi> — But it may be <hi>William Lilly</hi> boggles thus at the King of Swedes Fate, hoping to baffle the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of ſuch a like direction, that will ſhortly happen in his own Nativity. But <hi>William,</hi> I can aſſure you upon my honeſt word, that the <hi>M.C.ad</hi> ♂ <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> ♄ portends more than a fit of the ſtone; &amp; this you will ſhortly find true, unleſs you can implore the aſſiſtance of ſome of thoſe Angels you boaſt of, to remove malignant ♄ out of the Heavens. But <hi>Lilly</hi> confeſſes, that others have catechiſed him for this his folly; but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:123655:29"/>ſaith, <hi>they are Nameleſs impertinent Botch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and perſons of no quality; and therefore they are beneath his Pen to take Cognizance of; Aquila non capit Muſcas.</hi> All this Sir is but your <hi>ipſe dixit;</hi> for the Fame of thoſe that have diſſected your Ignorance, is every whit as ſplendid as <hi>William Lillies,</hi> although they began to labour in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of Aſtrology long after him. It is true, they are not (as I hear of) famous for trepanning Kings; or for Star-gypſies, or Planet-Quackers, or Angel-Mongers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that perhaps is the reaſon why <hi>Lilly</hi> terms them perſons of no quality. If by men of no quality, <hi>Lilly</hi> mean in reſpect of their birth, or parts; His poor leather-jacqueted Father of <hi>Diſeworth,</hi> an obſcure Village in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> were he alive, could not but ſhed tears for grief that ever he ſhould breed up a Son to ſo much Arrogancy, and vain-glory; as knowing it impoſſible for any man to come of a meaner ſtock than himſelf.</p>
               <p>But why doth <hi>Lilly</hi> urge the Adage, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilo non capit muſcas?</hi> Doth he hope to excuſe his Credit, by inſinuating his Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt a Flye? O doth he ſuppoſe there is as great a difference between the perſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:123655:29"/>he calls impudent Boy and himſelf, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Eagle and a Fly? <hi>Lilly,</hi> I know it is above an <hi>Eagle</hi> to catch at a <hi>Fly!</hi> But <hi>Bubo!</hi> it is not above a <hi>Buzzard</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a <hi>Boy! But why ſhould</hi> William <hi>eſteem himſelf an Eagle?</hi> In knowledge it cannot be, I am ſure; and I have heard ſome ſay, not in Eſtate neither. In the firſt, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſee I have proved him an Owl ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this all along: and would have him therefore, if his Almanack go any more to the Preſs, to correct his Errata, and remember for <hi>Aquila</hi> to inſert <hi>Bubo.</hi> In the ſecond, he cannot be an Eagle neither, if <hi>Vox Populi</hi> be true; for they ſay, As he hath gotten an Eſtate like a K—he hath parted with it like a F—and is become a poor Tenant for his life. <hi>But why make your ſelf ridiculous to anſwer a Boy?</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you ſuppoſe your ſelf uncapable of excuſing thoſe errours the Boy chargeth upon you, without contracting as many more? That (I readily acknowledge) were the way to make your ſelf ridiculous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed! But why muſt you childiſhly throw the <hi>Boy</hi> at your Adverſary? I can tell you Sir! He is no ſuch Boy, but that he is able
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:123655:30"/>to crack your crown, as he hath done your credit in Aſtrology. And perhaps he would too, were not the Amulet of AGE your protection and ſecurity. However, I ſhall return you in exchange for your Boy, the Adage, — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But this is the deſpight of it, <hi>Lilly</hi> is ſuch a Boy in Learning, he cannot Engliſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why Ranting-impudent Fool?</hi> If Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a privation or defect of wiſdome, or ingenuity, <hi>Lilly</hi> is the abſurdeſt Fool that ever I either read or heard of. And for the concomitants of his Fool — <hi>Ranting and Impudence;</hi> I think it impoſſible for any man to ſurpaſs him. Well, but ſaith <hi>Lilly,— This Impudent, Ranting Fool, or Boy, dare not own his Name to be</hi> G.I. <hi>or</hi> I.G. Here, Mr <hi>Merlin,</hi> you do homage on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Father of lies, (whom it may be you are better acquainted with, than with the Angels you tattle and boaſt of.) For he hath owned <hi>G. I.</hi> as the initiall Letters of his Name in the ſpurious Prognoſticator, to your ſorrow: but <hi>Lilly</hi> hath little liſt to cope with either the Author, or the Book; the one being ſo repugnant to his Principles, the other to his skill. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is not for fear of <hi>Lillies</hi> Pen, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:123655:30"/>the Author forbears to ſet his name at length, but for the forementioned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> having fluttered and beat his Eagleſhip out of breath, in the <hi>Aeſtival Quarter,</hi> is now come to the <hi>Autumnal,</hi> and ſaith, ☉ <hi>enters</hi> ♎ <hi>Septemb.</hi> 12. <hi>at noon.</hi> Yet if you conſult his own Ephemeris, you will find <hi>Sol</hi>'s place that day at noon, in 29 <hi>d.</hi> 58 <hi>m.</hi> ♍. Could any Boy of a moneths reading in Aſtrologie be guilty of greater Impudence and Ignorance, then this? Or did ever any man rant ſo vainly under the Canopy of Aſtrologie, and know ſo little thereof, as doth this Owl <hi>Lilly? No more Eagle Sir! until your skill be mended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit ſaith <hi>Lilly,—This Figure and Vernal Scheme agreeing with the King of Swedes Nativity,— Let his Majeſties Enemies brag of this ill poſition of Heaven, which by Gods bleſſing may render him vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious in the Acquiſition either of a Battel if he be in</hi> Campania; <hi>or a City or Town if in the Siege of one; or if at Sea, a Maritime Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi> If falſe Figures promiſe Victory, <hi>Lilly</hi> may prove a true Prophet in ſome of theſe things: but certainly from falſe Figures, fallacious Victories muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:123655:31"/>And ſuch will thoſe be, that the K. of <hi>Swede</hi> obtains about this time; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>Lillies</hi> Paraſitical Pen. For <hi>Saturn</hi> is now in Quartile to the place of the dire Direction but lately mentioned; and to the Cuſp of the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> hopes in his Radix and Revolution alſo. But <hi>Lilly</hi> is to be read backward, as men read Hebrew: when he promiſeth Victory, let the King of <hi>Sweeden</hi> be ſure to expect loſs.</p>
               <p>For concluſion, <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, had he not been prevented, to have delivered ſomewhat of the Tutelary and Preſidentiary Angels.</hi> &amp;c. and boaſts of the Expoſitors that follow the Septuagint, and of the Fathers, <hi>viz. Dionyſius, Origen, Baſil, Nazianzen, Clemens Alexandrinus, Damaſcen, Hillary,</hi> &amp;c. But he underſtands the Doctrine of Angels, and thoſe learned Fathers, both alike: <hi>(i. e.)</hi> as much as he doth Aſtrologie, <hi>viz.</hi> onely to brag and boaſt with, that he may the better paſs for a Scholar among the ignorant. And to this end, ſteals three or four ſayings (which he underſtands not) out of <hi>Dingley</hi> of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, (who cites thoſe Authorities he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently mentions) and would needs enforce them upon the world as the fruits
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:123655:31"/>of his own Phlegmatick and Drowſie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and Studies: and for a farewel, triflingly concludes, — <hi>This learning will finde cold entertainment with Atheiſts, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Paddies.</hi> Certainly if Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> be the Author of it, 'twill be fit onely for the reading of ſuch kind of Fellows; and thoſe (perhaps) are his principal Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Diſciples. But what Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhould mean by <hi>Paddies,</hi> I cannot deviſe, (for <hi>Rider</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> own no ſuch word) unleſs he mean one that beſtrides the King of <hi>Swedes</hi> Sumpture Horſe; which if he do, now he hath crackt his Credit in Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, I would have him become Probationer for the place. So I deſcend from his general Prognoſtications, to his monethly Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which I ſhall but lightly examine, and ſo paſs them, until the whole year ſhall more particularly inform me of his failings. For I queſtion not, but his Predictions, and thoſe of <hi>Montelion</hi> Knight of the Oracle, as they are calculated for one and the ſame Meridian of Truth, and have one and the ſame foundation in Art, ſo one and the ſame ſucceſs will crown them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:123655:32"/>
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>His Monethly Fictions examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>January</hi> Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> predicts, —<hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ranting and ryming Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets of illiterate Fellows, we hope ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable victory will be gained by the Swedes,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed Sir, the <hi>M. C.</hi> ad ♂ ♄, comes on too faſt for this to be true. But if the King of <hi>Swede</hi> had no ſuch Direction ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, what Reaſon or Authority hath <hi>Lilly,</hi> to prefer his own ignorant hopes in the room of Art? or doth all his skill in Aſtrologie depend upon hopes and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, without any ſolid demonſtration? Doth this ignorant fellow think, that <hi>Mars</hi> his now ſquaring ♃ in the King of <hi>Swedes</hi> Nativity, and at the ſame time tranſiting the tenth houſe thereof; (together with a Quartile of <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> from the third and fifth Houſes both of his Radical and Revolutional Figures) do any way aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or encourage his hopes? <hi>Lilly!</hi> theſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:123655:32"/>Arguments will prove you an abſolute Lyer. I confeſs, had the Swede only rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and riming Pamphlets to oppoſe him, he might eſcape the better, although he never conſulted <hi>Lillies</hi> lying-Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack.</p>
               <p>In <hi>March</hi> he ſcramblingly writes, — <hi>If the ſeaſon permit, the ſcrambling Pens of Ideots will prove falſe Prophets.</hi> Did ever any man, that pretended to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſence, render himſelf a more ſcrambling Ideot than <hi>Lilly</hi> doth here? Prethee, Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> tell me what ſeaſon that is, which the ſcrambling Pens of Ideots (or others) prove Prophets in; let them be either true or falſe. Is it Spring, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Summer, Autumne? I proteſt for this conceit, I could afford to Chronicle thee, <hi>WISE WILLIAM LILLY</hi> in the next Impreſſion of <hi>Erra Pater;</hi> but that were to abuſe thee more than this book is deſigned to do; for 'tis the office and duty of this to ſpeak truth. <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſome happy ſucceſs near this time is deſigned for his Majesty of</hi> Swede. If any ſuch thing be deſigned, it muſt be either by the energy of the Heavens, or ſome other power: by the Heavens there is no ſuch thing deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:123655:33"/>but the contrary; as <hi>M. C. ad</hi> ♂ ♄, (nearly touching now) denotes, it being attended on by an ♂ of ♃ and ☿, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Twelfth and Sixth Houſes of his Radix and Revolution alſo; preſaging much Treachery and Infortunacie, in the room of the happy ſucceſs <hi>Lilly</hi> boaſts of. If it be promiſed by any other power, <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſhould have told us ſo: but a Golden Bribe can bend a Buzzards Pen any way.</p>
               <p>In <hi>April</hi> he rantingly writes— <hi>Let men and devils, or all earthly devils do their worſt, the Noble</hi> Swede <hi>will now again be ſucceſsful, according to his preſent condition, even by Sea or Land, or near it.</hi> This good Chriſtian Aſtrologer, complained of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts and Ranters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that were his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts; but could any Atheiſtical or Ranting Fellow in the world, write more Rantingly and Atheiſtically, then himſelf hath here? <hi>Let Men and Devils, and all earthly Devils, &amp;c.</hi> Sure this ranting-ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Fellow ſuppoſes, that the <hi>Swede</hi> hath, not men, but devils to encounter with; or elſe what doth he mean, by ſuch ranting helliſt, expreſſions? But why earthly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils? Doth he believe there are any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in Heaven? But (ſaith he) <hi>Let thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:123655:33"/>Devils do their worſt, the K. of</hi> Swede <hi>will be ſucceſsful.</hi> If the <hi>Swedes</hi> Enemies, (which this malicious Fellow terms De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils) do but their worſt, the <hi>Swede</hi> may then be ſucceſsful, as he groundleſly writes: But Sir! they are like to do their beſt, and not their worſt; and ſo will leave you a devilliſh Lyar to Poſterity. But <hi>he will be ſucceſsful by Sea or Land, or near it;</hi> ſaith this Barbarian in Art and Learning. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I am, the ☍ of ☉ and ♄, and ♂'s tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the radical place of ♃, conſidered, together with his ſad Revolutional Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, denies him ſucceſs at Sea or Land. What he may (by Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> Ptedictions) expect near it, I know not: perhaps he dream't of ſome airy happineſs and ſucceſs, when he writ this ventoſitous Fancie.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May</hi> this Impoſtor predicts, — <hi>The Heavens ſhew much hope for ſettlement of</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Spain, <hi>in league and amity.</hi> This he perfectly reads in the Heavens too, (O rare Monthly Obſervator!) although the peace betwixt thoſe Princes was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded ſix Months before, as the News-Books had acquainted him: for you muſt know, he ſtudies them more then he doth old <hi>Ptolomy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:123655:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> skips from <hi>April</hi> to <hi>September</hi> without mentioning the leaſt particle o the Swediſh King. And then (too late) tells him — <hi>The Heavens give cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him,</hi> &amp;c. For then his game (in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of <hi>Lillie</hi>'s flattery) is near at an end. This counſel <hi>(Lilly)</hi> you ſhould have given him at the beginning of the year, if you had dealt as fairly by him, as he hath nobly by you.</p>
               <p>In <hi>October</hi> this pedantick Paraſite cants — <hi>That the K. of</hi> Swede, <hi>in deſpite of all oppoſition, cannot fail of many ſucceſſes in or near this month:</hi> Surely Sir! ſpiteful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, will do the Victor no durable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. But what muſt theſe ſucceſſes be, I wonder? why ſaith <hi>Lilly, Such as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion requires.</hi> Now if the K. of <hi>Swede</hi> (being a Souldier) ſhould happen (for want of conveniency) to be invaded with a Souldiers Fortune, <hi>viz.</hi> to be ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er within, then without; and in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition obtain the happineſs (or ſucceſs) of a clean ſhirt, <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhall have the honour of predicting it Aſtrologically. But one pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty piece of Policy I meet with in <hi>wiſe Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams Octobers Obſervations,</hi> that makes me ſmile at the writing thereof: 'tis this: It
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:123655:34"/>then being about Almanack time, and <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> believing that he ſhall be laſh'd, as the laſt year, (for he knows he hath notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerved it) and that you may think he reads the ſame in the Heavens, he learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (by this his ſharp Praeſcience) predicts — <hi>Some botching Atheiſt now beſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters him.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And is there any Delian Wizzard can</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Planet-Quacking match this cunning Man?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>In <hi>November</hi> he again temporizes with the <hi>Swede,</hi> thus: — <hi>Either with full peace, or much happineſs, the</hi> Swedes <hi>are bleſſed according to their preſent condition.</hi> Prethee, <hi>Lilly,</hi> tell me, how thou cameſt to be ſo baſe a Flatterer? Doſt thou ſee ♂ upon the place of ☉, and ☉, ♂ and ☿ in ♂, and all in ☍ to <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>'s Radical place, in the King of <hi>Swedes</hi> Geniture? I am perſwaded, thou makeſt thy ſelf a Paraſite on purpoſe, or elſe thou knoweſt not ♂ from thy Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Bodkin.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:123655:35"/>
               <p>But to conclude all his wiſe work, In <hi>Decembers</hi> right-hand-page he writes, — <hi>The guilty find friends.</hi> And in the left, verifies it in himſelf, thus — <hi>If Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter were not in Libra,</hi> (his Printer hath made it <hi>June,</hi> but I ſcorn as much to retort that upon him, as he thinks it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him to anſwer a Boy) <hi>Saturn would afflict poor</hi> Anglicus. <hi>Providence ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for him friends.</hi> Go on <hi>William!</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs all your ſins, and guiltineſs of all kinds; and conſider that your end draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on, and the <hi>M. C. ad</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> ♄ <hi>&amp;</hi> ☉ is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apace; and flatter not your ſelf as you have done the King of <hi>Swede.</hi> You will begin to claim the Title of an aged Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in Aſtrology: Flatter not your ſelf therefore. For it is not ♃ in ♎ that can any way ſtead you. Is not ♄ returned to his own place, and the oppoſite place of the Sun? Is not your Revolution notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly cruel, and miſchievous alſo? And how ſhould ♃ in ♎ help you? Doth ♃ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold either the Aſcendant, or ☉ in your Nativity? Is he not in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> of <hi>Luna?</hi> Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not your ſelf, I ſay: Learn Aſtrology (for once) from a Boy; And if at laſt ♃ in ♎ fail you, ſay you had an enemy dealt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:123655:35"/>more faithfully with you, without a Gold Chaine, than you did with the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> for one. So I leave <hi>William Lilly</hi> in the midſt of his Flatteries and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as I found him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 34. line <hi>Antepenult,</hi> read 8 <hi>digits.</hi> P. 37. l. 25. r. <hi>Saturni.</hi> P. 48. l. 9. r. <hi>the ariſings.</hi> P. 50. l. 25. r. <hi>Aquila.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:123655:36"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT</head>
            <p>A <hi>Perſon of Honour, by Name</hi> Montelion, <hi>or the Knight of the Oracle, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken great pains in the calculating divers Nativities, ſome of</hi> Jury-Packers, Chalke-Merchants, Wife-Poyſonners, Widdow-Undoers, Trepanners, <hi>&amp;c. and the Genitnres of Mrs.</hi> P. W. L. Grace L. <hi>and</hi> I. F. <hi>at large; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a true and perfect Emblem of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:123655:36"/>the croſs match mentioned in Dr.</hi> Dee's <hi>Book of Spirits: it is therefore deſired, that the</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſter <hi>(Lilly mentions) would inſert theſe in his intended Book of Nativities, that his Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may be the more compleat.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
